בוקר טוב *Boker tov*. Today is קידושין kidushin, דף daf. ג *Kiddushin
Daf Gimmel*. And we pick up towards the bottom of דף עמוד
ב *Daf Amud Bet*. We had a very critical introductory first דף
*Daf* yesterday. On the one hand, we're now in the middle of
a classic stama-itic introduction to the מסכת
masechet *Masechet* where it starts focusing on a lot of technical grammatical
aspects. We're in the middle of figuring out why if the word
האשה נקנית niknet בשלשה דרכים drachim? *ha'isha nikneit b'shlosha drachim*, if דרך
derech. *derech* is masculine or feminine, is it שלש *shalosh* or שלשה
*shlosha*. It's both ways in the תורה Torah *Torah*, it's both ways
in different משניות *mishnayot*. How do we explain that? Something that really
is hard for us to get too excited about, unless we're all
grammarians. But interestingly, it started earlier with a question about why it
uses the word נקנית niknet *nikneit* as opposed to later in the
מסכת masechet *Masechet* where it uses the word מקדש *mekadesh* or מקודשת
*mekudeshet*, which got us to a very central question about whether קידושין
kidushin *Kiddushin* is understood as a type of קניין kinyan *kinyan*, a
purchase, and the emphasis of learning it out from the whole case
by Abraham buying, you know, the field of עפרון Ephron, *Ephron* and
on a type of property acquisition type of a model which the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* referred to as לישנא דקרא *lishna d'kra*, sort of
if you would the way the תורה Torah *Torah* conceptualizes it. And
then what later becomes the rabbinic understanding of קידושין kidushin *Kiddushin* and
מקודשת *mekudeshet* much more relating to status and as the way תוספות
Tosafot *Tosafot* explained it, מקודשת *mekudeshet* is not just forbidden to others,
but it's מקודשת לי *mekudeshet li*, forbidden to others as a result
of the relationship. So really a very significant and that's the type
of a dynamic, seeing those two models competing with one another that's
going to be playing out in like the first half of the
first פרק perek *Perek* about whether it's this קניין kinyan, *kinyan* acquisition
type of a model or whether some very different type of I
would call it a status model. And also what we saw introduced
was the idea which the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* also did in this
amazing way because although the משנה mishna, *Mishnah* emphasizes the woman essentially
as the object because of the language of the משניות *mishnayot* are
going through different types of objects that are acquired. האשה נקנית niknet
*ha'isha nikneit*, יבמה נקנית niknet *yivama nikneit*, עבד eved עברי *eved ivri*,
עבד כנעני *eved kna'ani*, נכסים שיש להם אחריות *nechasim she'yesh lahem achrayut*.
It sort of keeps on moving between is it this thing that's
being acquired or that thing or this person or that person. The
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that the emphasis of האשה נקנית niknet *ha'isha
nikneit* rather than האיש קונה koneh *ha'ish koneh* is to focus on
her role as a subject and to focus on the fact that
she cannot be done against her will, and that she actually is
a party to it which is again not the classic תורה Torah
*Torah* model. The classic תורה Torah *Torah* model is that she's a
minor actually, the תורה Torah *Torah* doesn't recognize anything other than a
woman being married by the father. חזל Chazal *Chazal* tell us that's
when she's a minor, but the but the תורה *Torah* does not
recognize anything other than the woman essentially as an object being married
off by the father. And the תורה *Torah* went out of its
way to point out that no we're talking here about her as
a subject, her as an adult and her ability to express her
will. So again very interesting sort of seeing the shift between a
תורה *Torah* model and what we have at the time of חזל
*Chazal*. Okay so now we continue though going back to some of
the grammatical stuff but we will sort of switch back into more
some substantive stuff very soon. So we pick up in the bottom
of דף א *Daf Aleph* and we have the following. It says
two lines into the wide lines. מאי טעמא *mai ta'ama* end of
the second in the wide lines. מאי טעמא תני שלש *mai ta'ama
tani shalosh*? Why does it say שלש *shalosh*? משום דרכים derachim, *mishum
drachim*. You said because we're going to say the word דרך derech
*derech* and דרך derech *derech* is at least could be feminine in
this context it could be feminine because of a larger context of
the woman is what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says that affects the
gender of the word being used here because דרך derech *derech* can
be masculine or feminine. But one minute, מיתני וברייתא *mitni v'varaita*, I
got another question. Forget the masculine feminine question, why does it say
דרכים derachim *drachim*, why not say
בשלשה דברים devarim *b'shlosha dvarim* in three ways or three things? If
you actually think about it right just in terms of the English
term a woman is acquired in three ways, a woman is acquired
by three things, it's different right? It's you know so we'll see
what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* does. But in three ways makes is
more appropriate, there are three different alternative paths in order to do
this type of a transaction or in order to do this type
of a קניין kinyan, *kinyan*, this type of act of
קידושין kidushin. *kiddushin*. Okay but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says is why
not say
דברים devarim *dvarim* instead of דרכים derachim *drachim*. So the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says משום דקבעי למתני ביאה bi'ah *mishum d'ka ba'ei
l'mitni bi'ah* because we're going to get to after כסף kesef *kessef*
which emphasize why we said נקנית *nikneit*, we're then going to get
to
ביאה bi'ah. *bi'ah* and ביאה bi'ah *bi'ah* is a word that's associated
with the word of דרך derech *derech*, a path. דכתיב d'chsiv: ודרך
גבר בעלמה *d'chtiv v'derech gever b'alma*, the way of a man in
a young woman. So it's talking about so maybe that's expressing also
sort of the natural sort of biological urge there. But anyway or
דכתיב, but somehow that's a focus on the word דרך. derech
So the גמרא Gemara says כן דרך אשה מנאפת. ken derech isha
menafet. So similarly a woman who commits adultery, which is a very
disturbing way to open up this מסכת masechet here, a very sort
of graphic description of ביאה bi'ah or sort of and then sort
of and then contrasting it to an אשה isha committing adultery. I
don't know what to do with that as an introductory פסוק pasuk
in the מסכת masechet here. Yeah, but let's just one second. So
anyway it says התנא ביאה, hatana bi'ah, the גמרא Gemara says okay,
but that's good in terms of sex, that would explain why it
used the word דרך derech because you know that's natural. כסף ושטר
מאי איכא למימר kesef ushtar mai ika lemeimar but how is the
word דרך derech appropriate for כסף ושטר? kesef ushtar? So one says
משום ביאה. mishum bi'ah. Okay, but we chose דרך derech. because it
was appropriate for one of those three. So the גמרא Gemara says
ותני תרתי אטו חדא? vetani tarti atu chada? I don't get it,
you're going to schlepp the other two along because of one? דרך
derech. is only a word appropriate for ביאה. bi'ah. So let's still
again, it's this bizarre question: why is דברים devarim. so much of
a preferred term? Anyway, like I said, this is an opening סתמא
דאידי stama de'idi passage, so you can't get too worried about some
of these questions. Anyway, but okay, so you'd say דרך derech just
because of the ביאה bi'ah. word? But how about the other two?
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, הנהו נמי צורך ביאה נינהו. hanahu
nami tzorech bi'ah ninhu. Okay, those two also, even if you do
it by כסף kesef and שטר, shtar, ultimately what the marriage is
leading to is a union of the couple which is going to
be a sexual union. So the idea of ביאה bi'ah. sort of
shadows the entire, you know, or or like or like frames a
lot of is implicit in a lot of what's going on. Now
that's already I think quite interesting because if you think about it
the גמרא Gemara says that the reason we use the word נקנית
was because כסף kesef, was going to be the first word that
we were going to list. So תוספות Tosafot there says the גמרא
gemara didn't stop there to say well why are you going to
use קנין kinyan because it's only שייך shayach for כסף, kesef what's
not שייך shayach for שטר shtar and ביאה. bi'ah That the גמרא
gemara didn't stop to ask. Maybe because כסף kesef was the first
one it's appropriate to use the verb of נקנית which is relevant
to the idea of כסף kesef. even though it's not directly relevant
to the other two. But bottom line is actually that verb of
נקנית says you know is if we're going to say that that's
a concept of קידושין, kidushin, we're probably not going to limit that
to when קידושין kidushin was done through כסף. kesef, That presumably frames
the way we think about the nature of קידושין kidushin regardless of
how it's done, right? So that's very powerful that it used the
word נקנית even if the point of departure was כסף, kesef, it
used the word נקנית to frame the whole institution and act of
קידושין. kidushin Well here the גמרא gemara is saying something very similar
about the idea of ביאה. bi'ah Now again this is just a
little דרשה drasha of the גמרא gemara because of the word דרך
derech. instead of דבר. davar. But regarding the fact, disregarding the fact
that it's just a דרשה, drasha, what the גמרא Gemara is saying
is maybe the whole idea of קידושין, kidushin you know, is framed
as ultimately an institution that is leading to the couple coming together
in a sexual union, right? Which is very interesting because you know
when we think about how קידושין kiddushin. gets actualized at חופה, chupah,
which is נישואין, nisuin, which is sort of seen when it comes
from theory to practice, there are two aspects of the נישואין. nisuin.
Right? נישואין nisuin represents a house, right? If you think about like
the חופה, chupah, the יחוד yichud room, but it represents also the
physical intimacy and the coming together. The idea is the יחוד yichud
room is a way in which they could in theory at least
be having sex. And the ראשונים Rishonim talk about both and that
marriage is really both things, right? Marriage is setting up a joint
household, you know, sort of, having sharing your life together, raising kids
or whatever the joint household aspect of it, all the aspects of
כתובה, ketubah, of the reciprocal obligations and so on, and it's also
the very much of the most intimate physical coming together of the
two parties and it's about sex. So it's very interesting here that
it sort of says well you know all of קידושין kiddushin. is
ultimately leading towards ביאה. bi'ah Now of course ביאה bi'ah could itself
represent coming together in both ways, but nevertheless I think it's very
interesting on the one hand emphasizing very much an acquisition model and
on the other hand emphasizing a fact of the physical coming together
of the two which in some ways could be understood as the
greatest aspect of the sense of the partnership, right? על כן יעזוב
איש את אביו ואת אמו ודבק באשתו והיו לבשר אחד. al ken
ya'azov ish et aviv ve'et imo vedavak be'ishto vehayu levasar echad. Right?
It's like two halves coming together as a whole. So it's an
interesting just contrasting how a sort of saying one the idea of
קנין kinyan frames everything and the idea of ביאה bi'ah? frames everything.
Ben, you had a question? Okay. So alright so now the גמרא
Gemara, says like this. ותא veta okay so the גמרא Gemara, says
ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'it eima, and if you want I'll say, הא מני
רבי שמעון היא. ha mani Rabbi Shimon hi. You know why it
says דרכים? derachim, Not because of ביאה biah but because of רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתניא detanya we taught רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon
omer: מפני מה אמרה תורה mipnei mah amrah Torah why did the
תורה say כי יקח איש אשה ki yikach ish isha ולא כתיב
כי תלקח אשה לאיש velo ktiv ki tilakach isha le'ish when a
man takes a woman? Why didn't it say when a woman is
taken by a man?
So מפני mipnei right why does it make the man the sort
of the active party here which is so central to קידושין kiddushin,
that the man is the active even though the woman has to
be מדעתה mida'atah can't be forced on her? We know that the
active קידושין kiddushin, is basically done by the man. So here he's
getting back to the fact, you know, the תורה frames it that
way. When a man takes a woman, מפני שדרכו של איש לחזר
אחר האישה ואין דרכה של אישה לחזר אחר האיש, mipnei shedarko shel
ish lachazor achar haishah ve-ein darkah shel ishah lachazor achar haish, because
the man goes searching out for the woman, the woman doesn't go
searching out for the man, right? So even in, you know, our
very egalitarian society today, even though it happens, I guess, more that
women ask guys out for dates or whatever, you know, there's still
is this sort of like presumption more that the man is the
one that is, you know, that is the more of the initiator
in this whole dating process and so on and the one searching
after the woman. משל
לאדם שאבדה לו אבידה, mashal leadam sheavdah lo aveidah, like a person
who lost an object. Why has he lost the object? Because it's
the half of his body that was taken from him in מעשה
בראשית. maaseh bereishit. So מי חוזר על מי? mi chozer al mi?
Who looks for who? בעל אבידה מחזר על אבידתו. baal aveidah mechazer
al aveidato. The person who lost the object looks after, goes looking
for his lost object. Okay, so this is also, by the way,
I just have to tell you a great story. So apparently there
was a time in, I think it was in the Mir where
the guy—it was like, you know, the guys were—they were already like,
you know, getting to their thirties or whatever and they still weren't
married, and it was enough already. So that year they were learning
like מסכת קידושין masechet kiddushin and they got to this line. So
the ראש ישיבה rosh yeshiva gets up—I don't know if this really
could be said in the Mir because there's not like one ראש
ישיבה rosh yeshiva in the Mir, but anyway, anyway, he gets up
and he says, "So it says
דרך איש לחזר אחר אבידתו." derech ish lachazor achar aveidato. He says,
"If you're looking for an אבידה, aveidah, you'll find it. If you're
looking for a מציאה, metziah, it's going to take you a long
time."
All right, anyway.
All right, so all right, anyway, I'm always afraid to make any
jokes in this מסכת masechet because I'm sure it's going to be
not PC whatever I say. Anyway, all right, somebody can critique me
for all my non-PC statements. Anyway, but I do think this is
also interesting, again, contrasting to the קניין kinyan model, because if you
think about it, right, here it's—you could say it's a type of
a קניין, kinyan it's my lost object, so it's something I own,
right? But there is some greater sense here of reinvoking or evoking
the idea of like being reunited with that thing that was sort
of always yours, your lost half, the whole idea of באשערט, bashert,
right, finding that thing that, you know, it's much more different than
taking possession of something like the woman just as an object. So
even though the אבידה aveidah metaphor still has that aspect to it,
I think it frames it in a, you know, very different way,
in a way you could almost see echoes of both the ביאה
bia and the קניין, kinyan you know, that partnership, but a little
bit of that קניין kinyan aspect sort of coming together in this
metaphor about being חוזר אחר אבידתו. chozer achar aveidato. So I think
that there's something, again, powerful about those ideas being introduced, you know,
right here. The other aspect of course about the man as the
initiator besides the whole question about, you know, the dating process, it's
actually, you know, interesting because the גמרא Gemara says, you know, I
mean, there is a reality between the sort of social norms and
expectations. You know, it's not the same if—obviously women want to get
married as much as men. You know, the גמרא Gemara, actually said
that some of the reasons that they had to establish certain of
the הלכות halachot of כתובה ketubah were to encourage men to get
married. And, you know, the גמרא Gemara says—has a phrase that says,
you know, "A woman would be satisfied with טב למיתב טן דו
מלמיתב ארמלו," tav lemeitav tan du milemeitav armelu, exactly, with like any
husband. You know, guy wants—like I said, guy wants a מציאה metziah
or something. So it's interesting, right, that given that, that it's still,
you know, the—and like I said, it still really hasn't changed too
much in today's society about, yeah, certainly in this whole dating process
or whatever, who the basic expectation about being the initiator, right, is
on. So that's an interesting phenomenon, but it also does—it does parallel
the aspect of the husband being—of the man being the primary acting
person in the act of קידושין. kiddushin, And again, what's nice by
framing it this way is it moves us again a little bit
away from the קניין Kinyan, model because—because if you say, "Why is
the man the only one that's acting, right, if they're both coming
into marriage, why doesn't she have more of an active role?" "What's
that? Oh, of course, it's because like she's just the object and
she's being purchased." So you know, so that's why he's the actor
and she's—and he's the subject and she's the object, right? So this
sort of gives us a different way of looking at it. You
know, it says, "No, it has to do something with the sort
of male-female dynamics and so on that he's sort of more of
the active party," etc. So again, you could like that or not
like that, but it frames it in a very different way than
the sort of acquisition subject-object type of a relationship.
Okay, so what else do we learn from כי תקח ki tikach
each other?
I mean, like there's even more, right? Yeah, I understand. I'm just
saying I think it's very powerful that right at the beginning we
have a lot of competing models: קניין Kinyan versus קידושין. kiddushin Is
it all about קניין Kinyan or is it basically about ביאה? bia
Is it about the man taking possession of an object or is
it about a guy being חוזר אחר אבידתו chozer achar aveidato and
the loss—his lost half and being reunited with his lost half, right?
Very different ways of thinking about what's going on. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, והא תנא... veha tanna... והתנן,
vehathnan, that which we taught in the משנה, Mishna בז' דרכים, Be-zayin
derachim, now back to דברים devarim and דרכים, drachim. בז' דרכים בודקים
את הזב. Be-zayin derachim bodkim et hazav. We talked this yesterday. You
check a זב zav to make sure that the flow is not
due to some external cause, so you check seven sort of things:
was it because of what he ate, was it because of this,
was it because of that? ליתני דברים, lisni devarim,
seven things. Since you're saying that the only reason it said דרך
derech was because of either the language of ביאה bia or the
act of the way of a man is to look after his
to find his lost object, so normally let's say דברים. devarim? So
why doesn't it say דברים devarim? there? So התם קא משמע לן
דאורחא דמיכלא יתירא לאתויי לידי זיבה. hasam kamashma lan de'orcha demichla yasira
la'asuyei lidei ziva. So we're going back to the word that it
uses the word דרכים drachim when it's trying to suggest that there's
a natural cause here, there's natural ways in which this thing is
working. You know, this is the way things work, the way is
that a man goes looking after the woman. So we're checking for
other causes for the flow because this is the way things work
that when you eat certain foods they lead to a flow. So
דרכים drachim. suggests that there's a naturalness to the way that these
things are working. Okay. ואורחא דמישתיא יתירא לאתויי לידי זיבה. ve'orcha demishtaya
yasira la'asuyei lidei ziva.
So drink brings to a flow, too much and too much food
brings to a flow, too much drink brings to a flow, that's
the use of the word דרך. derech All right, let's take another
example. והתנן, vehasnan, אתרוג שוה לאילן בג' דרכים, etrog shaveh le-ilan be-gimmel
derachim, וליתני דברים. vlisni devarim. An אתרוג etrog is similar to an
אילן ilan in three ways, so why not say in three matters,
three דברים? devarim? Okay, because an אתרוג etrog on the one hand
is a tree, but on the other hand it grows, you know,
it sort of it constantly is growing throughout the year, it doesn't
just have one season of blossoming, it grows by irrigated water, not
just rain water, as we'll see, you can pick the אתרוגים etrogim
at all different times. So there's ways in which it's similar to
a tree and ways in which it's similar הלכתית halachically to a
vegetable. So why does it say דרכים, drachim. why not say דברים?
devarim? So it says משום דבעינן למתני סיפא ולירק בדרך אחד. mishum
de'ba'inan lemasni seifa ve-leyarak be-derech echad. Okay,
because we have to say like a vegetable in one דרך. derech
So that just, you know, repeats the question. סיפא נמי ליתני דבר,
seifa nami limsni davar, why don't we say in one דבר? davar?
Why are we still saying דרך derech. instead of דבר? davar? And
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says if it had said דבר davar
in all these things we would have had an
opening סוגיא sugya that would have said why doesn't it say דרך.
derech, But okay. Anyway, so it says התם קא משמע לן דאורחיה
דאתרוג כירק. hasam kamashma lan de'orcha de'etrog keyarak. Ah
no, we're back to the idea that דרך derech means that this
is the way of things, because the way of an אתרוג etrog
tree is has, you know, its behavior is similar to that of
a vegetable.
Is he summing up anything?
Ah yes, wait a minute, yeah, מה ירק דרכו ליגדל על כל
מים ובשעת לקיטתו עישורו. mah yarak darko ligdal al kol mayim uvesha'as
lekitaso isuro.
This explains what are the ways it's like a tree, what are
the ways it's like a vegetable. So the ways it's like a
tree, רש״י Rashi says is is that it has the הלכות halachos
of ערלה, orlah, it has the הלכות halachos of נטע רבעי, neta
revai, the fourth year fruits. It goes by, trees go by blossoming
to determine what year they're related to. You know, everything is right
part of a seven-year cycle. Is it the first two years of
the cycle? You give מעשר שני maaser sheni as your second מעשר.
maaser. If it's the third or the sixth, right? If it's one,
two, four, five you give מעשר שני, maaser sheni, if it's three
or six you give מעשר עני, maaser ani, and if it's year
seven of course it's שמיטה. shmita. Well what determines which year this
thing that's growing from the ground is connected to? Does it grow
the year you plucked it? Does it grow the year it started
growing? So depending on things there are different ways. Right, by grain
it goes by a third of the ripening. By trees it goes
the year that it blossoms. By vegetables it goes by the year
that it's picked. Okay, because vegetables are constantly growing, there's no like
one concrete point where it's like, you know, like a transition stage
with a vegetable. All right, so by an אתרוג etrog we go
by the way it's like a tree is that for שמיטה shmita
purposes we go by the year that it blossoms. But by for
all other מעשר maaser purposes we go by the year that the
fruit is is picked. All right. Because like a vegetable, since the
fruit is constantly, you know, growing throughout the year, it's not seen
and it, you know, and you can, and it's not seen as
like just one particular season, so it's not fixed to a particular
time and it goes by the time that it's picked. Of course,
I never got that exactly straight because if an אתרוג etrog was
blossomed in שמיטה shmita and was picked in the eighth year, so
from a שמיטה shmita perspective it's שמיטה, shmita, but from a מעשר
maaser perspective it's מעשר שני. maaser sheni. But you don't give מעשר
שני maaser sheni on שמיטה. shmita. I'm assuming that שמיטה shmita would
sort of trump, you know, in terms of the הלכה. halacha. But
let's say it's the opposite. It blossomed in the sixth year and
it was picked during שמיטה. shmita. So from a שמיטה shmita perspective
it's a sixth year fruit, but from a מעשר maaser perspective there's
no מעשר maaser because there's no מעשר maaser on שמיטה. shmita. So
what do you do? So I never exactly got how you could
have both the both the שמיטה shmita counting and the מעשר maaser
counting based on different things since they since they're sort of have
to be synchronized. But anyway, that's the הלכה halacha of an אתרוג.
etrog. So it says we use the word דרך derech to explain
that the reason it's like a vegetable by that it goes by
when it's picked is because of the ways in which it's similar
to a vegetable. דאורחיה דאתרוג כירק. de'orchei de'etrog keyarak. מה ירק דרכו
ליגדל על כל מים, mah yarak darko ligdal al kol mayim, the
same way a vegetable grows by all water, meaning irrigated water, and
not basically by the rainy water. water and the seasons and so
on ובשעת לקיטתו עישורו u-bishat lkitato issuro
and therefore it goes by the מעשר maaser follows the time that
it's picked. So אף אתרוג דרכו לגדל על כל מים, af etrog
darko ligadel al kol mayim, the same by an אתרוג etrog grows
by all waters ובשעת לקיטתו עישורו u-bishat lkitato issuro
and therefore the מעשר maaser goes by when it is picked. So
we use the word דרך derech to explain that these ideas, whether
it's the idea of ביאה bia. by קידושין, kiddushin, or checking by
a זב, zav, or the way an אתרוג etrog is like a
vegetable, these are not just arbitrary, they're דרך. derech There's something natural
about the way that this is working that has to do with
the way this thing operates, which explains why this law applies. Yes.
Could you just remind me the phrase of חנטת פגיה, hantat fageha,
like the running of the sap that is שייך shayach to like
the טו בשבט Tu B'Shvat season as it were?
Running
of the sap has ever
a halakhic that has no...
no, I mean, to the degree it is, it's to the degree
that it's recognized through the blossoming that occurs in the fruit.
So the blossoming is really the external symptom.
Yeah, I mean, I never thought of it that way, but yeah.
Okay, all right.
It also occurs to me by the way about this idea of
דרך, derech cause as you could see, I'm trying to sort of
ask or act like what לקח lekach do you get from this
in terms of what it's sort of saying about קידושין, kiddushin going
back to the whole idea of, you know, דרך גבר בעלמא, derech
gever b'alma, is that there's something very like in the most sort
of natural sense about like if you ask like, you know, without
societal institutions, right, you know, what would, you know, what's the most
natural form of marriage?
I mean, it could also just be having sex, but there's also
something the most natural way is not some act of קנין kinyan
or שטר, shtar, I mean שטר shtar is the most sort of,
you know, forced, societal type of a, like not natural thing, right,
the whole writing of a document and so on. But it's, you
know, just the physical coming together, you know, that is and if
you actually the רמב"ם Rambam says that, you know, for בני נח,
Bnei Noach, you know, not the רמב"ם, Rambam, it's based on the
גמרא, Gemara whatever, but what the רמב"ם Rambam says is, yeah, before
the Torah was given, what would happen by בני נח? Bnei Noach?
A man would meet a woman, they'd want to get married, they'd
have sex, and then they'd be married. So there's something like the
most, not that sex makes it that way, but in a context
of wanting to be married, that's the most natural type of a
thing, right? And in a way that's that פסוק pasuk in בראשית,
Bereishit, ויעזוב איש את אביו ואת אמו ודבק באשתו, v'yazov ish et
aviv v'et imo v'davak b'ishto, suggesting the sexual union. So there is
interest in contrasting it that way as well, sort of seeing this
as a sort of natural thing as opposed to a more of
a societal way of formalizing the institution. Yes.
Well what about how the משנה Mishnah starts by saying everything we're
about to tell you is in service of this like natural way
of right? You go after the one in that like...
Oh, so you mean it's not just that marriage is sort of
that it's all about ביאה bia. in this context of when they're
eventually married, but that ultimately in terms of thinking about like just
the process, the act of קידושין, kiddushin which is the prime act
that we sort of see as that act. Yeah, I think that
that's a really good question because you know, there's a serious debate
in the פוסקים, poskim, which is, I mean פשוט pashut of all
the גמרא, Gemara since let me reframe that, shouldn't call it serious
debate, פשוט pashut of everything is that כסף, kesef שטר, shtar, and
ביאה bia are all דאורייתא. d'oraissa. Nevertheless, רש"י Rashi already quotes in
the name of his רבותי rabotai based on a סוגיא sugya in
the beginning of כתובות Ketubot about הפקעת קידושין hafka'at kiddushin that sort
of said it was easier to do הפקעת קידושין hafka'at kiddushin by
קידושי כסף, kiddushei kesef, that that's a שיטה shita of the גאונים
Geonim or whatever his רבותי, rabotai, that קידושי כסף kiddushei kesef is
דרבנן. d'rabbanan. And רמב"ם Rambam actually in a couple of places says
that קידושי כסף kiddushei kesef is מדברי סופרים, midivrei sofrim, okay? And
that thing actually says that the most explicit act of קידושין kiddushin,
in the Torah is ביאה. bia It says כי יקח איש אשה
ובעלה. ki yikach ish isha u-ve'alah. Now we already discussed yesterday that
כי יקח איש אשה ki yikach ish isha in the Torah is
not קידושין, kiddushin? it's נישואין, nissuin, okay? קידושין kiddushin, in the Torah
is אשר אירש אשה. asher eiras isha. And actually פשט pshat in
the Torah is that פשט pshat of the פסוקים pesukim is that
קידושין kiddushin. in the Torah, אירוסין eirusin in the Torah—did I say
nissuin? I meant to say eirusin a minute ago—אירוסין eirusin in the
Torah is through כסף Keseph, because that's what a מוהר mohar was.
Okay, but nevertheless, רמב"ם Rambam says that if you focus on the
word יקח yikach as קידושין, kiddushin that's associated with ביאה. bi'ah. So
that gets back to Jenna's point, which is right? If we have
these two models, a קנין kinyan model and a sort of natural
ביאה bi'ah union model, right, which one do you see as the
primary of what defines קידושין? kiddushin So right, you could so it's
interesting that that also can be interpreted as you see one is
דאורייתא d'oraissa and the other is less דאורייתא d'oraissa and so on.
So yeah, thank you, that's a very good point. Saying the other
two are in service of this, not in service of ביאה during
marriage, but in service of it in terms of an act of
קידושין, Kiddushin which is the prime act of קידושין. Kiddushin Right, excellent.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
והא דתנן, vehada tnan, כוי, koi, יש בו דרכים שוה לחיה, yesh
bo drachim shaveh l'chaya, I'm sorry, יש בו דרכים שוה לחיה. yesh
bo drachim shaveh l'chaya. This כוי koi is this type of a
hybrid. I think it's a cross, there's debates in the גמרא, Gemara
I keep on forgetting, I think it's a cross... cross between like
a deer and a ram maybe? I'm not remembering. Anyway, so it's
some type of a union of a what? It's a שה, seh,
right. Some type of a union of a, some type of a
union of a חיה chaya and a בהמה, behema, crossbreed or maybe
it's actually its own breed. Anyway, so it says there, so חז"ל
couldn't figure out whether it was a חיה chaya or בהמה. behema.
So יש בו דרכים שוה לחיה ויש בו דרכים שוה לבהמה. yesh
bo drachim shaveh l'chaya v'yesh bo drachim shaveh l'behema. There are ways
it's similar to a חיה chaya which is because you have to
be מחמיר machmir in all ways. So you're מחמיר machmir that it's
a חיה chaya so you have to cover the blood which you
only do by a חיה chaya when you שחט. shacht. And there's
ways it's like a בהמה. behema. The fat is forbidden which is
only true by a בהמה behema not a
חיה. chaya. ויש בו דרכים שוה לחיה ולבהמה. v'yesh bo drachim shaveh
l'chaya u'l'behema. There's ways it's like both of them. The דרשה drasha
is why you need to do שחיטה. shchitah. It's not a fish.
See that, a fish you wouldn't have to do שחיטה shchitah for.
ויש בו דרכים שאינו שוה לא לחיה ולא לבהמה. v'yesh bo drachim
she'eino shaveh lo l'chaya v'lo l'behema. And there's ways it's not like
either, which is you can't crossbreed it with either חיה chaya or
בהמה behema because it might be the other one. Anyway, ניתני דברים,
nisni devarim, why not say דברים? devarim? What's דרך about that? What's
natural? There's nothing natural that puts it in one category as opposed
to the other. You don't know what category to put it in.
ותו הדתנן, v'tu hadatnan, that's what we taught, זו אחת מן הדרכים
ששוו גיטי נשים לשחרור עבדים. zo achat min hadrachim she'shavu gittei nashim
l'shichrur avadim. This is one of the ways that a גט get
for women is similar to a writ of manumission of a slave
in the whole idea of בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם. bifanay nechtav uvifanay
nechtam. You see when we got out of יבמות Yevamot we thought
we would never have to hear about יבום yibum again and then
יבמות Yevamot constantly, יבום yibum always resurfaces. So we got out of
גיטין Gittin which like was dominated by בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם bifanay
nechtav uvifanay nechtam and we thought we were free from it and
boom we get it already in the next, in the second דף.
Okay so anyway, both a גט get of a woman and a
גט get of an עבד need to say בפני נכתב ובפני נחתם.
bifanay nechtav uvifanay nechtam. So it says this is one of the
דרכים. drachim. Why don't we say דברים? devarim So the גמרא Gemara,
says ניתני דברים, nisni devarim, why not say דברים? devarim. אלא ela
okay so fine, דברים devarim, and דרכים drachim is not about whether
it's natural or not natural. אלא ela here's the difference between whether
we use the word דרך or דבר. davar. כל היכא דאיכא פלוגתא
תני דרכים. kol haycha d'ika plugta tani drachim.
When there are distinctions, then we say דרכים. When it's like, you
know, it's done in these ways and not in other ways. These
are the three ways you do it as contrasting to other alternatives,
okay? But then we say דרכים. Where there's no distinctions we say
דברים. devarim What would be an example? תני נמי דקתני סיפא רבי
אליעזר אומר עשר שוה לאילן לכל דבר, tani nami d'ktani seifa Rabbi
Eliezer omer eser shaveh l'ilan l'chol davar, not לכל דרך. l'chol derech.
Okay? It's similar in all matters. So when you so if when
you say דברים, all matters, right, then you're then there're no distinctions.
But if you're identifying that it's in these ways it's like this
and in these ways you're contrasting certain ways to other ways, you're
going to use the word דרכים. שמע מינה, shma mina, which is
exactly how we talk, right? You do it in these three, these
are three ways, you know, there are different ways you could imagine
but these are the three ways, right, seems it suggests alternatives. It's
a way to get there as opposed to another way to get
there, right? As opposed to דברים does not suggest a type of
alternative. All right, that was not the actual question of דרך and
דבר davar I can't get excited about, but what's nice about these
opening these opening סוגיות, sugyot, you know, I think this point is
often lost. So when people are aware of this point that רב
שרירא גאון, Rav Sherira Gaon, this is a point that רב שרירא
גאון Rav Sherira Gaon writes in his letter, that he writes that
you know that these some of these opening סוגיות sugyot are exactly
as we described it. A lot of Tannaitic material, no real new
ideas, just collecting some different ברייתות Braittot or what you know different
Tannaitic material. And it often focuses on these like grammatical aspects. So
people say, you know they go okay whatever so then you know
just sort of gloss over and get through it, which is the
opposite extreme of how it's normally learned in the ישיבה, yeshiva, which
is like the hyperfocus. ישיבה yeshiva you could spend I don't know
a whole day trying to figure out this question about דרך and
דבר davar and whatever and why did the גמרא Gemara, say it
this way and not say it that way? I think that the
truth is somewhere in between. I think that you know it is
like a true sometimes it's a trivial question that drives it, but
they're trying to introduce the מסכת masechet, to you. It's a and
they're putting a lot of ideas out there on the table. If
you think about a look at the opening מסכת masechet, in בבא
קמא, Bava Kama, it says the משנה mishnah. in בבא קמא Bava
Kama says, right, you know that ארבעה אבות נזיקין הן. arba avot
nezikin hen. So the גמרא Gemara says well אבות avot it means
that there are תולדות. toladot. Well are the תולדות toladot the same
as them or not the same as them? And based on that
question it uses that question to go through all of the different
אבות avot of נזיקין, nezikin, all of the תולדות, toladot, asking this
question are they the same or not the same? And in the
course of that one question it's introduced you to the entire first
half of the מסכת, masechet. to all of the different אבות avot
and all the תולדות. toladot. So here too in the course of
in the context of some grammatical question which we can't get too
excited about or דרכים or you know word choice question, it's introduced
us to a lot of core concepts of what קידושין Kiddushin are
and I would actually say competing models of what קידושין Kiddushin. are
and you know it's very powerful in that regard. Yes Ben.
In that array I bet the constancy of דרך I think is
very interesting in that it suppose it makes all these statements about
like the inherent way things are and like inherent gender norms like
a man goes a door a woman doesn't a man... And then
it concludes by bringing all these cases of like in-between things, like
an אתרוג, Etrog, what has a bit of this and a bit
of that.
Oh, that's interesting.
It's almost like a sub-model of like things
can follow natural order and then totally breaks it down by saying
there are always in-between cases.
Oh, that's great. That's beautiful. יישר כח. Yasher koach. Like that. That's
really very nice. Wonderful. Okay. Alright. Now, so now we get to
a more classic
סוגיא. Sugya. Alright. מניינא דרישא למיעוטי מאי, Minyana dersha lema'utei mai, מניינא
דסיפא למיעוטי מאי? Minyana desifa lema'utei mai? Alright. So now it says
if now that we all said that צריכי, Tsrichi, to say that
there are different ways and it's saying certain ways and not other
ways. Anyway, so if a woman is acquired in three ways and
acquires herself in two ways, the number presumably is excluding other possibilities.
So what are the other possibilities that are being excluded? So מניינא
דרישא למיעוטי חופה. Minyana dersha lema'utei chuppah. So the three ways that
a woman is acquired excludes חופה Chuppah as a possibility. So if
a woman were to, for some reason רש״י Rashi here introduces the
father, says if a man were to give over his daughter for
marriage and they went straight to the חופה Chuppah without a קידושין
Kiddushin and they just stood under the חופה Chuppah and he said
הרי את מקודשת לי Harei at mekudeshet li or something, maybe the
act of חופה Chuppah itself is enough. Again, I don't know why
רש״י Rashi doesn't just say she went herself as opposed to the
father gave her over, but maybe what partly bothers רש״י Rashi is
is that it's hard to see חופה Chuppah as a type of
a significant act, right? By itself. Like what's exactly the act there?
Standing under a חופה? Chuppah? What does it mean anything? So רש״י
Rashi might want to introduce the father because that makes it more
like something is done. He gave over his daughter, he handed her
over to put her under the חופה, Chuppah, right? If a woman
just walks under חופה Chuppah with a man, but nevertheless, why not?
Maybe that's just symbolic, that symbolizes marriage. Maybe that does it. Anyway,
so that's the question: would חופה Chuppah work as an act of
קידושין kiddushin by itself? As opposed to an act of נישואין Nisuin
which, you know, after the קידושין kiddushin had already taken place. So
the גמרא Gemara says ולרב הונא דאמר חופה קונה, Ulerav Huna de'amar
chuppah konah, how about, we're going to see in a few, in
like two days, that רב הונא Rav Huna is going to say
חופה Chuppah actually is an act of קידושין. kiddushin מקל וחומר, Mikal
vachomer, he learns it out from a קל וחומר. Kal vachomer. So
we'll worry about that opinion when we see it in two days.
So למיעוטי מאי? Lema'utei mai? What would this, what would the three
things be excluding because חופה Chuppah would not be excluded? So the
גמרא Gemara says למיעוטי חליפין. Lema'utei chalipin. It would exclude a case
of an exchange. Okay, חליפין? Chalipin? סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina,
הגמרא, Hagemara, right. Exactly. סלקא דעתך אמינא, Salka deitach amina,
הואיל וגמר קיחה
קיחה משדה עפרון, ho'il ugamar kikha kikha misdei Ephron,
since we learn out קידושין Kiddushin, from acquiring a field and we
learn it out from the whole, you know, acquiring of the field
of עפרון, מה שדה מקני בחליפין אף אשה נמי מקניא בחליפין? ma
sadeh mikani bechalipin af ishah nami mikanya bechalipin?
So if you could buy a field with חליפין, Chalipin, maybe you
should be able to buy a woman with חליפין. Chalipin. קמשמע לן,
Kamashma lan, so it tells you no, a woman's only בכסף. Bechesef.
So the גמרא Gemara says, you know what? That was a good
הוה אמינא. Hava amina. ואימא הכי נמי? Ve'eima hachi nami? Why not?
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, חליפין איתנהו בפחות משוה פרוטה. Chalipin
itnehu befachot mishaveh perutah. You could do חליפין Chalipin with an object
worth less than a פרוטה. Perutah. If you use a כלי, Keli,
you could use like a toothpick, okay? You could use a, חליפין
Chalipin is done with a כלי, Keli, but it doesn't have to
have the value of even a פרוטה. Perutah. So since it could
be done with that, ואשה בפחות משוה פרוטה לא מקניא נפשה. Ve'ishah
befachot mishaveh perutah lo mikanya nafshah. A woman won't agree to sell
herself for less than a פרוטה. Perutah. I mean, a פרוטה, Perutah,
fine, but less than a פרוטה, Perutah, no. Now, this is a
very interesting גמרא, Gemara I mean line. What the heck does this
mean? First of all, רש״י Rashi asks,
just because in theory it could work with less than a פרוטה,
Perutah, let's say you're not doing חליפין Chalipin less than a פרוטה.
Perutah. So רש״י Rashi says no, but the whole nature of the
transaction suggests a transaction that exists with less than a פרוטה. Perutah.
And the woman, רש״י Rashi says, the phrase רש״י Rashi uses is
דגנאי הוא לה, Degnai hu lah, it's demeaning to her to agree
to be part of such a transaction. Now we should take a
moment back and talk about two types of חליפין, Chalipin, okay? Because
it really is hard to understand why חליפין Chalipin does not work
by קידושי אשה. Kiddushei ishah. חליפין Chalipin is two types. There's the
classic "I'll swap you my donkey for your cow," okay? Where they're
seen as basically barter, right? Basically seen as an exchange of equivalents.
You take one, I get the other. Okay. That's one thing. You
could say that that's more natural than כסף, Keseph right? Things probably
started as a barter and then כסף kessef, became to represent abstract
value. Okay, that's one form of חליפין. Chalipin. Why would that work
with an object less than a פרוטה? Perutah? Maybe still it's symbolic.
You take my toothpick and I get your cow. We're still exchanging
objects. It's not about value, it's about objects. Okay. So that's one
way of understanding it. Another way of understanding it is because חליפין
Chalipin is a generic קניין, kinyan right? I could do a חליפין
Chalipin to, sometimes you want to do an act of קניין of
חליפין, Chalipin, we call it קניין when we, when we mean this
second thing, like, you know, you take the handkerchief, think about, talking
about the wedding, about the כתובה. Ketubah. The man, you know, takes
the handkerchief or whatever, the watch from the rabbi and he obligates
himself to the כתובה Ketubah obligation. Contracts are undertaken through the taking
of an object, right? That creates, sort of, and I accept that
object and through that accepting I signify that I am committing myself
to the terms of this contract. I am obligating myself by the
contract. That fundamentally works more like a handshake. It's not like an
exchange. It's an act that is for... expresses the גמר דעת, gemar
da'at, what we call a meeting of minds, the commitment to do
it, the finalizing of that commitment. Okay, so those are the two
sort of ways in which, but that can actually work even to
sell something. I take your handkerchief, you actually don't even have to
let go of the object and anybody ever see sometimes the rabbi
he does this or the guy doesn't even let go of it.
So it's not really about an exchange there, there it's much more
about an act that signifies גמר דעת gemar da'at and then you
obligate yourself or you sell me your object or whatever happens. Now,
if you asked which one of those should or should not work,
should either of them work for a case of a woman, well,
the exchange model definitely should not work. And there I can really
identify with the idea of like רש"י Rashi says of פחות משווה
פרוטה, pachot mishaveh prutah, specifically פחות משווה פרוטה לא מקניא נפשה, pachot
mishaveh prutah lo makanya nafshah, but the whole transaction is demeaning. It's
like swap my pen for your daughter or my pen for yourself.
It very much commodifies the woman. Whereas by
כסף, kessef, you can talk about it as symbolic. Ultimately we wind
up talking about it, it's giving a פרוטה, prutah, it's symbolic. It
doesn't suggest, have to suggest an exchange, it could just be you
give an object of value and therefore that effectuates
this trans- well transaction's the wrong word, but this act, okay, this
institution. Whereas חליפין chalipin suggests an exchange, and that obviously would be
very inappropriate.
So why not
פחות משווה
פרוטה
pachot
mishaveh prutah then?
Say that it, I know, it does not explain the שווה פרוטה
shaveh prutah point. I'm just telling you what I think about whether
חליפין, chalipin, why חליפין chalipin should or should not work. But in
terms of the idea of חליפין chalipin as a
גמר דעת, gemar da'at, like, why not? I mean, especially the way
we think about קידושין kiddushin? nowadays, it's, I mean, marriage in general,
like often
people think about it in terms of like it's a contract, it's
an agreement or something. Again, I think it's obviously that's selling it
a little short. But why should a גמר דעת gemar da'at with
an act that sort of says yes, we're committing to it, we're
making it final, it's not exactly clear to me why the
גמר דעת gemar da'at model of
חליפין chalipin should not be completely relevant to קידושין kiddushin and certainly
why it should be a type
of a גנאי gnai and לא מקניא נפשה lo makanya nafshah type
of an idea. So I don't know, I can't fully explain why
that does not work, but certainly to the degree that all חליפין
chalipin ultimately hearkens back to a concept of exchange and maybe that's
what we could say, that even if it's a גמר דעת, gemar
da'at, it's ultimately hearkening back to an ultimate model about exchange and
swap and barter that's inappropriate for קידושי אישה, kiddushei ishah, that's not
what קידושי אישה kiddushei ishah is about. Not just she's offended, but
that's not what קידושי אישה kiddushei ishah is about. That's sort of
how I would explain it. It does not exactly fit רש"י, Rashi,
who emphasizes that it's, well the גמרא, Gemara it's less than a
פרוטה prutah and it's demeaning. It's not because it's less than a
פרוטה prutah is what I'm saying. It's because it's fundamentally an act
of a barter. One second, so that's, but that's the way רש"י
Rashi explains it, and therefore רש"י Rashi says even if you use
something more than a פרוטה, prutah, fundamentally, if you framed it as
חליפין, chalipin, now think here actually is where it gets closer to
what I'm saying. Because here's my iPhone, let me tell you, it's
worth more than a פרוטה, prutah, okay? You get it free maybe
when you start your plan, but don't break it, it costs you
a few hundred dollars. Okay, so anyway, if I were to say
to a woman הרי את מקודשת לי באייפון זה, harei at mekudeshet
li be-iPhone zeh, here go right ahead, whatever, that works. Okay, but
if I took the exact same iPhone and I said בחליפי אייפון
זה הרי את מקודשת לי, be-chalifei iPhone zeh harei at mekudeshet li,
okay,
I gave the exact same object, but I framed it as חליפין
chalipin and not as כסף, kessef it doesn't work. And רש"י Rashi
says, oh, because in the context of חליפין, chalipin, it suggests פחות
משווה פרוטה. pachot mishaveh prutah. It's a model that works to be
פחות משווה פרוטה. pachot mishaveh prutah. So like to me, what does
that mean? The only way I can make sense of that is
that when I say בחליפי אייפון זה, be-chalifei iPhone zeh, I'm saying
okay, that we're swapping, and that frames it as just an exchange
and a barter and that very much is a commodification and that
doesn't work. באייפון זה be-iPhone zeh could make it much more symbolic.
That's the way I would like to understand what the גמרא Gemara
is saying. תוספות Tosafot, says that actually, he says רש"י Rashi does
not, he has a different גירסא girsa than רש"י Rashi and it's
not אישה בפחות משווה פרוטה לא מקניא נפשה, ishah be-pachot mishaveh prutah
lo makanya nafshah, it's אישה בפחות משווה פרוטה לא מקניא, ishah be-pachot
mishaveh prutah lo makanya, period.
And turning to תוספות, Tosafot the question was, hold on, let me
just double check תוספות Tosafot... make sure I'm saying this right...
בדבור המתחיל... bedibur hamatchil... האישה, ha-ishah, it's this big תוספות...
Tosafot on the
prior page...
here we go...
one
second...
Yes, so תוספות Tosafot says that the question was never, the way
תוספות Tosafot says it is that the question was never that we
should learn out other קנינים. kinyanim. It's only we oh, well any
קנין kinyan that works by a שדה sadeh should work by a
woman. So if חליפין chalipin works by a שדה, sadeh, it should
work by woman. So
תוספות Tosafot says no, no, no. The only question was that let's
conceptualize חליפין chalipin as a type of a כסף kessef? because ultimately
it's very similar. You give an object, you give something of value,
and you get something back. So why is חליפין—the chalipin גמרא Gemara
is really just asking why is חליפין chalipin any different than כסף?
kessef. Let's just call it a type of a כסף. kessef. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, no, no. חליפין chalipin works בפחות משוה
פרוטה befoches mishaveh prutah ופחות משוה פרוטה לא קני, ufoches mishaveh prutah
lo kani, לא אישה לא מקניא נפשה. lo isha lo maknya nafsha.
Less than a פרוטה prutah isn't כסף. kessef. So that just proves
that the institution of חליפין chalipin is not a form of כסף.
kessef, It's true in both of them you give something and the
transaction takes place, but one of them has to do with the
object's value and requires a שוה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, and the other
has to do with the fact that it's a כלי. kli. You
could have something that has value that isn't a כלי, kli, like
you could give fruit wouldn't work by חליפין. chalipin. So one has
to do with value and is a קנין כסף, kinyan kessef, and
the other has to do with a כלי kli and it doesn't
have to do with value. So all the גמרא'ס Gemara's establishing is
that חליפין chalipin is not a type of a קנין כסף. kinyan
kessef. And once it's not כסף, kessef we don't—the only thing that
works is כסף שטר וביאה. kessef shtar u-viah. Okay.
So you say the fruit does not work for חליפין, chalipin, so
if the rabbi gave you the apple and you give him the
חמץ chametz that you're selling him—correct.
I mean there's a discussion in the גמרא Gemara about fruit, but
yes, according to that that's correct. Okay, so to recap what we
said was the גמרא Gemara says why should חליפין chalipin work? According
to רש"י, Rashi, the question is should it work because it is
a form in which you קונה koneh a שדה, sadeh, maybe we
should include all forms of being קונה a שדה? sadeh? To which
the גמרא'ס Gemara's answer is that no, that's a—רש"י Rashi says it's
a גנאי הוא לה, gnai hu lah, it's demeaning. What does it
mean it's demeaning, especially if you're using something more than a פרוטה?
prutah? So the way I sort of suggested it, as a way
of reading רש"י Rashi and the גמרא Gemara is, is that fundamentally
חליפין chalipin is about exchange as opposed to כסף kessef which could
be more about a symbolic type of an act. And since even
if you give the same iPhone, if you give it as חליפין,
chalipin, you're saying we're swapping, and that's very much sort of completely
commodifying, and that would not work. Okay, that's one way of explaining
it. תוספות Tosafot it was a narrower question. Let חליפין chalipin just
be a form of כסף kessef, and the answer is it's not
a form of כסף, kessef. it works with different parameters than כסף.
kessef You had a question before?
Yes, who was מבטל mevatel חליפין? chalipin?
Was the תורה מבטל—no, mevatel no, the גמרא Gemara understands that—the
רבנן Rabbanan was
מבטל—yeah, mevatel it never said that they were מבטל. mevatel. The רבנן
Rabbanan identified, רש"י Rashi says the רבנן Rabbanan identified that that could
not be included in the גזירה שוה. gezeira shava. You're right, I
mean, it's funny because we had a גזירה שוה gezeira shava of
קיחה קיחה, kicha kicha, which means that קנינים kinyanim that work by
a field work by an אישה, isha, but we used our סברא
sevara to figure out that it doesn't—it's not an all-inclusive category.
I mean I was going on רש"י'ס Rashi's language, like it's a
גנאי הוא לה, gnai hu lah, הילכך לא גמרה ומשעבדא נפשה. hilkach
lo gamra umeshaabda nafsha.
Yeah, I don't think it means somebody annulled it, it means sort
of like it is invalid as a form of
קידושין—even kiddushin. דאורייתא. deoraisa. Right, I mean that's what תוספות Tosafot says.
תוספות Tosafot says and if a woman says actually it's okay, I
don't mind, you know, and תוספות Tosafot says I don't get it,
the woman's agreeing to do the חליפין, chalipin, so it can't be
a גנאי הוא לה, gnai hu lah, she's participating in it. So
רש"י Rashi would have to say no, objectively it's inappropriate and therefore—so
that's actually again, that's the way I would read that is it's
objectively inappropriate because it makes it all about exchange. All right, so
let's take a look now at—the גמרא Gemara continues.
מנינא דסיפא לאתויי מאי לאתויי חליצה. Minyana de-seifa l'atuyei mai l'atuyei chalitza.
So how about she gets her own freedom in two
ways, death and the גט. get. What does that exclude? It excludes
an act of חליצה. chalitza. Husband can't do חליצה chalitza to his
wife. סלקא דעתך אמינא תיתי בקל וחומר מיבמה, Salka dachtech amina tesei
be-kal vachomer mi-yevama, let's make
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. מה יבמה שאינה יוצאה בגט יוצאה בחליצה,
Mah yevama she-eina yotza be-get yotza be-chalitza, a sister-in-law who you cannot
get free with a גט get before if you haven't done יבום,
yibum, right, you can't get her out of that need of requiring
יבום yibum by giving a גט, get, nevertheless חליצה chalitza works. זו
שיוצאה בגט אינו דין שיוצאה בחליצה, Zu she-yotza be-get eino din she-yotza
be-chalitza, this woman that a גט get can work, how much more
so חליצה chalitza should be able to work. So the גמרא Gemara
says קא משמע לן, ka mashma lan, it tells you ah, it
can't, only גט. get. The גמרא Gemara says אימא הכי נמי, eima
hachi nami, why not, let's say that's a good קל וחומר. kal
vachomer. If it works by יבום yibum it should work by—by a
normal case of marriage. אמר קרא, Amar kra, ספר כריתות, sefer krisus,
a book of divorce. ספר כריתות Sefer krisus only a writ divorces
her and nothing else כרתה. karasa. Now here you are going to
be introduced to
a humorous aspect of the first פרק of קידושין, kiddushin, which is
the גמרא Gemara asks a lot of hypothetical קל וחומרס. kal vachomers.
Okay, and some of them are quite humorous because it just shows
what happens when you totally stick to the form of a קל
וחומר, kal vachomer, because a קל וחומר, kal vachomer, well, if this
thing works here even though this other thing doesn't work, so in
this case where that thing does work, this thing should work. Like
it's like maybe each thing works. uniquely because of its circumstances, right?
So it's like, so you know, but that, anyway, the גמרא Gemara
asks, it's always true, but it just plays out so much here.
It's like, really, oh, because חליצה chalitzah works, a גט get doesn't
work, you know, a גט get doesn't work by יבום yibbum because
it's not relevant to גט, get, they don't have that form of
a bond, but they have a weaker bond, so חליצה chalitzah works,
and חליצה chalitzah is appropriate because חליצה chalitzah is, you know, ככה
יעשה לאיש אשר לא יבנה את בית אחיו, kachah ye'aseh la'ish asher
lo yivneh et beit achiv, right? So to now suggest that חליצה
chalitzah should work by קידושי אשה, kiddushei isha, it's like you need
a פסוק, pasuk, ספר כריתות. sefer keritut. It's like crazy. It's like
totally just following the formalism of this. So anyway, as if that
weren't bad enough about the גמרא Gemara there, there is a book
called
עצמות יוסף, Atzmos Yosef, which I actually started reading once when I
was in high school because you get these like when you learn
a מסכת, these like these books that have like a group of
like אחרונים achronim and ראשונים rishonim on the מסכת. So, you know,
you buy them for the ראשונים rishonim but they have these like
weird אחרונים achronim in the back. Anyway, so the עצמות יוסף, Atzmos
Yosef, as if that, first of all, as if the גמרא Gemara
wasn't enough, תוספות Tosafot does it to the next level. Because then
תוספות Tosafot is always asking, wait, but you could have made a
קל וחומר kal vachomer this way and why didn't we make a
קל וחומר kal vachomer that way and so whatever. And then as
if תוספות Tosafot wasn't enough, then there's this אחרון achron called the
עצמות יוסף Atzmos Yosef like does תוספות Tosfos squared, you know, and
he asks all these hypotheticals. Anyway, so they tell the story that
he was once for שבת Shabbos at somebody's house, the author of
the ספר, sefer, and they brought him the soup and they gave
him and they gave him a fork. So he says, why are
you giving me a fork for my soup? He says, well, it's
a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. He says, you know, when it comes
to meat, you can't eat meat with a with a spoon but
you can eat it with a fork. So soup that you can
eat with a spoon, קל וחומר kal vachomer you should be able
to eat with a fork. So anyway, so that is just, but
you can't blame him because that's like a lot of what we're
going to be seeing. So I just wanted to warn you about
that. Yes.
So we said that חליצה chalitzah doesn't work because אשה פחות משוה
פרוטה לא מקניא isha pachot mishaveh perutah lo mikanya because of the
כסף kessef model, but then you still have שטר shtar though. So
for שטר shtar is,
no, שטר shtar is not a כסף kessef model. שטר shtar is
going to learn,
but then things that are a כסף kessef model won't work.
Okay, exactly. And other things, other things need another basis. Okay.
And חליצה chalitzah is essentially כסף kessef. model, you're saying?
Right. Okay.
Or not. I mean, but that was the question.
Right. Okay, now, but because now we get to the כסף. kessef
Okay, what is it? Now, interestingly, until now, we've been prepped with
the idea that we learn it out from שדה עפרון, Sdei Ephron,
but it's actually that's not going to be the first emphasis of
the גמרא Gemara about where we learn כסף kessef from. מנלן? menalan?
How do you know that כסף kessef, works as
קידושין? kiddushin. ותו, ve-tu, and in addition, that's what we
taught, היכא דתנן, heicha detnan, זכאי בבתו בקידושיה בכסף בשטר ובביאה, zakai
bevito bekiddusheha bekessef beshtar uveviah,
the father
has
the rights to his daughter to marry her off, whether through an
act of כסף, kessef, שטר, shtar, and ביאה. Now, the question is
the rights mean that he can marry her off when she's a
minor. Now, what now why does it mention the forms meaning like
you might have thought that maybe you can only marry her off
through כסף, kessef, right? Because that's like also that's more transaction and
those are, you know, especially if you think about the transaction model,
he's selling her, he's getting the כסף, kessef you know, that's sort
of the suggested model. Maybe an idea of like ביאה would be
something only when she's an adult, you know, and maybe that's not
something that he fundamentally is the one that sort of makes that
happen. Or שטר, shtar, who knows. Anyway, so all those forms work
for the father. Okay, now, but also the emphasis of the idea
of זכאי zakai means he gets to keep the money. All right.
So the גמרא Gemara says
where he says, מוסרה לאביה על כרחה, mosrah le'aviha al karchah, שאין
קידושין עוד נערה. she'ein kiddushin od na'arah. Yeah. So what's your question?
It just sounds a little harsh, so you can
well, that's what I mean, she this whole thing is על כרחה.
al karchah. You mean the fact that basically if she's if she's
like ten years old she's being we're talking about about, you know,
essentially rape? Yeah, that's true. I mean, you know, that's true. Meaning
normally when we talk about קידושי קטנה kiddushei ketanah it doesn't have
to mean she's having sex. Like I said before, you could wait
ten years before they start living together. But if קידושי קטנה kiddushei
ketanah is happening על ידי ביאה, al yedei biah, then yeah, we're
talking about pretty serious child abuse. I mean, that's worth anyway, okay,
fine. We're talking about anyway, but moving on. That's a that's a
definite problem. Yes.
So later דקאני לה de-kanei lah is you don't do it אלא
ברצונה. ela bertzonah. That that came in there somewhere?
Yeah, we'll see that. Okay. So, but you are right to point
out that it's when yeah, that that we're talking about having sex
with minors. Okay. מנלן דמיקניא בכסף וכסף דאבוה הוא? menalan d'mikanya bekessef
vekessef d'avuah hu? How do you know that she is married off
with money and the father keeps it? Which is, meaning so here
we're saying is how do you know she when she's doing קידושין
herself, the פשט pshat of our משנה. mishnah But then there's this
other
משנה in בכתובות bi-Ketubot that says the father does it. Or how
do you know the father can marry her off with money and
that the father keeps the money? So it's again quite interesting that
we're shifting immediately to the father. Like, you know, you and I
would say, wait, wait, wait. The father's like a different case. Let's
first focus on how do you know the woman herself. But actually
in the תורה the father is the case. That's all you have
in the תורה is that the father marrying her off. And by
starting כסף with the discussion of the father, that is really the
model that's very much suggests the whole, you know, קניין model. She
doesn't have a say, she's the object of exchange, the money is
going to the father, so it makes a lot of sense that
the גמרא Gemara besides
the fact that the father
model... How do you know that the
father can marry her off with money and how do you know
that he keeps the money? Okay, so let's take a look. So
you already have the answer or you think you do, so let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. Okay, so
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, דאמר קרא,
de'amar kra, the פסוק passuk says: ויצאה חנם נמי בכסף. Veyatza chinam
nami b'kesef. So here's another model where the father basically sells her
off, sells her off as a slave, right? And what happens at
the end? If she does not want to, if the guy doesn't
want to marry her at the end and she grows and she
becomes an adult, she's no longer a minor, then she just goes
free without money. So אין כסף לאדון זה, ein kesef le'adon zeh,
she leaves this master without any money going to him, אבל יש
כסף לאדון אחר. aval yesh kesef le'adon acher. Now the גמרא again,
the גמרא does not mince words here, right? So there's another master
over her, her father, that actually he would get money when she
would leave his control. Now, it can't be telling you about he's
just selling her as a slave because that's explicit in the פסוק,
passuk, you don't need it to say that. So what other case
would she leave the control of the father and the father get
money? It must obviously be קידושין. Okay, so quite clear here again,
that very much of object and you know transaction acquisition model. Okay,
ומאן ניהו אב? u'man nihu av? And that would be the father.
So the גמרא says: ואימא לדידה? Ve'eima l'dida? Fine, maybe the money
is given to the father, but maybe she keeps it, or the
way רש"י Rashi says is, it doesn't say יש כסף לאדון זה
ואדון אחר, yesh kesef le'adon zeh ve'adon acher, maybe it's just אין
כסף. ein kesef. So in another transaction, there would be money, but
maybe she would keep the money even as a minor. Okay, so
yes, there's a time when she would leave the father with money,
money would be done as קידושין, but maybe she would keep it.
So the גמרא says: ואימא לדידה? Ve'eima l'dida?
הכי השתא? Hachi hashta? What type of a question is that? אביה
מקבל קידושיה. Aviha mekabel kiddusheha. We know the father is the one
that receives the money. How do you know he receives it? Meaning
there's a difference between who receives it and then who pockets it.
Okay, but we know the father is the one who receives it,
דכתיב: את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה. Et biti natati l'ish hazeh.
I have given my daughter over to this man. Okay, now actually
that's by the whole case of מוציא שם רע. motzi shem ra.
And רש"י Rashi and תוספות both point out that מוציא שם רע,
motzi shem ra, if you remember, is a case of a נערה,
na'arah, not a קטנה, ketanah, right? That she's already she's already an
adult, she's all of twelve years old, but anyway, but nevertheless they
understand that the גמרא is reading it that he says I marry
her off to this man maybe when she was a minor, now
she's a נערה, na'arah, but I married her off when she was
a minor. Anyway, either way you see that the father is the
one who does the act of marrying her off, he's the one
that does the transaction, that does the act of קידושין. So presumably
the money is given to him, he's the one that's active in
the act. So if it's put in his hand, presumably he's the
one that pockets it. One
minute, so את בתי נתתי לאיש הזה, Et biti natati l'ish hazeh,
ואי שקל כספה? ve'ee shakal chasba? So how could it be, you
give the money into the father's hand and she gets it? Obviously
from that פסוק passuk you see he marries her off as a
minor and if he's the one marrying her off, he's the one
pocketing the money, you don't even need the פסוק passuk of אדון
זה ואדון אחר. adon zeh ve'adon acher. It's just he marries her
off, so obviously he pockets the money. So the
גמרא says: No. ואימא הני מילי קטנה דלית לה יד לקבולי קידושין.
Ve'eima hani mili ketanah d'leis lah yad l'kabbelei kiddushin. When is that?
I'll just read the question and we'll end with that now. Maybe
the פסוקים pesukim that the father marries off the daughter and it's
clear that he can do that and therefore clear that he would
receive the money, right, and that it would go into his pocket,
that's all when she's a minor, when we know that he has
total control over her and we know that she herself could not
marry herself off. אבל נערה דאית לה יד לקבל קידושין, Aval na'arah
d'is lah yad l'kabel kiddushein, but by a נערה na'arah where she
does have a hand to marry herself, so we'll discuss what that
means tomorrow, let's just read the
question: תקדש היא נפשה ותשקול כספה? tikadesh hi nafshah ve'tishkol chasba? Maybe
you could give her the money and she could keep it. So
what the question is that the גמרא is left with is: We
accept the idea that as a minor the father has total control
over the daughter, he marries her, he sells her, he keeps the
money, end of story. And when she's a בוגרת, bogeret, twelve and
a half, completely out of the father's control. The question we're going
to be exploring is when she's in that middle stage of between
twelve and twelve and a half, she's enough of an adult that
she has a certain sense of her own personhood in הלכה, halacha,
right? How do we know and that she could even accept כסף
קידושין kesef kiddushin on her own, although the father might be able
to or might not be able to, the father can say he
doesn't agree, but nevertheless she at least to some degree is her
own person. So at that stage, how do we know that the
father is entitled to marry her off and the father is entitled
to keep the money? So that's what we're going to be focusing
on starting with tomorrow. How do we know the father has these
rights when she is a נערה? na'arah? Okay, to be continued tomorrow.